<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Data &amp; Science: A blog</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Data &amp; Science: A blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dplyr’s select - tips and tricks</title>
      <link>/2020/05/20/dplyr-s-select-tips-and-tricks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/20/dplyr-s-select-tips-and-tricks/</guid>
      <description>It’s not the most interesting function, or even that much fun. But dplyr’s select has a lot of functionality that is often overlooked. All select does is ‘select’ columns, yet understanding some of its functionality deeper than surface level saves me a bunch of time in my day-to-day work. Let’s take a tour of where dplyr::select can save you time too, by calling out situations where I find myself using the function over and over again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So, you tested positive for COVID-19 - Do you actually have the virus?</title>
      <link>/2020/04/20/so-you-tested-positive-for-covid-19-do-you-actually-have-the-virus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/04/20/so-you-tested-positive-for-covid-19-do-you-actually-have-the-virus/</guid>
      <description>Testing positive for the Coronavirus doesn’t mean one actually has a SARS-CoV-2 infection. Like statistical models, one might say that all medical tests are flawed*, but some (hopefully all that we make decisions based off of) are useful. While creating these tests, scientists balance cost (in many ways), speed, generalizability, and of course, accuracy. Most of the time, in the case of a binary test (ex. you are pregnant or you are not, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking together my first web app in Django</title>
      <link>/2020/01/20/hacking-together-my-first-web-app-django/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/20/hacking-together-my-first-web-app-django/</guid>
      <description>Background A few months ago I started my journey to build my first web app, Rental Tensor (excuse the horrible name 😎) in order to estimate the rents for different properties at the zip code level. As a trained statistician disguised as a techy Data Scientist, I love playing with a mix of code and data, but I feel that it can sometimes be difficult for models or data pipelines to be very valuable without some sort of web backbone to host and serve it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pie Charts - What’s the big deal?</title>
      <link>/2019/01/17/pie-charts-what-s-the-big-deal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/17/pie-charts-what-s-the-big-deal/</guid>
      <description>In data visualization there are many unspoken rules which are ‘understood’ to be correct. Don’t plot in 3-D, don’t display column/bar charts on a logarithmic scale, don’t use two y-axes (or dare I say - more than two), and never never ever use pie charts. Yet pie charts remain common, especially in business, and some in the statistical/data science community just absolutely love to hate them.
Don’t just take my word for it, even the help function in base R for pie charts (?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cherry Blossoms</title>
      <link>/2018/02/23/cherry/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/23/cherry/</guid>
      <description>I wonder when the cherry blossoms will strike?
library(readr) library(dplyr) library(ggplot2) # getting data from # https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/cherry-blossoms_fig-1.csv # set.seed(123) cherry = readr::read_csv(&amp;#39;../../data/cherry.csv&amp;#39;, skip = 6) cherry = cherry %&amp;gt;% # adding the latest year (2017) data rbind(c(2017,84,NA)) cherry %&amp;gt;% ggplot(aes(Year, `Yoshino peak bloom date`)) + geom_line() + geom_smooth() + ylab(&amp;#39;Yoshino peak bloom date (days after Jan 1)&amp;#39;) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importing Functions From Github Into Your Package</title>
      <link>/2017/10/24/github_packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/24/github_packages/</guid>
      <description>Since the creation of the devtools package, it’s easier than ever to make and share R packages. This freedom has allowed pacakges to avoid the seemingly archaic process of submitting to CRAN, waiting for feedback, resubmitting… - While in the past, avoiding CRAN meant a significantly reduced audiance for your package, nowadays, easily posting to github means your pacakge is available to nearly every R user via devtools::install_github() not to mention other sources such as bitbucket or svn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Food Trends: A Baysian Approach to Forecasting Chipotle</title>
      <link>/2017/09/27/chipotle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/27/chipotle/</guid>
      <description>Since food is such an important aspect of life and public health, I thought it would be exciting to look at food trends over time. Obviously food choices drive public health, but I figured that trends were just this - trends, preferences that may change over time. While a bit broad, I narrowed down ‘food trends’ to be interest in Chipotle Mexican Grill - a fan favorite - over time. Since I don’t readily have any real Chipotle sales data, I decided to make my own - well, kinda.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The seeds of reproducibility - a 2 minute crash course</title>
      <link>/2017/08/25/seeds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/25/seeds/</guid>
      <description>While a Teaching Assistant for the 620 Biostatistics sequence at JHU (Statistical Methods in Public Health) one issue came up fairly regularly, the idea of seeds and reproducing results when sometimes non-obvious random elements are involved.
Many analyses are dependent on some sort of random number generation, weather it be from cross-validation, bootstrapping, imputing, or simulating, it’s inevitable that you’ll need these processes. Because of the nature of ‘random’ things, reproducibility can be tough.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond %&gt;%, Alternative Pipes in R</title>
      <link>/2017/07/02/pipes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/02/pipes/</guid>
      <description>Data scientists and the Mario Brothers agree - pipes rock.
If you have been using R for data ‘plumbing’/wrangling etc. you have undoubtedly came across the fantastic dplyr package and then by default, the the standard pipe.
The pipes we will be discussing today are from the magrittr pacakge, which is where dplyr’s ‘standard’ pipe comes from (repo is here). Straight from the highly recommended magrittr vignette, the purpose of pipes and the magrittr package itself is to “decrease development time and to improve readability and maintainability of code” - who wouldn’t like that?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Namespace Rabbit Hole</title>
      <link>/2017/03/30/the-namespace-rabbit-hole/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/30/the-namespace-rabbit-hole/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on an R package for factor analysis visualization for a while now, and ran into an interesting problem. One function in FAtools is essentially a wrapper for several functions in the nFactors package, which plots and displays both graphical and non graphical scree test solutions. It&amp;rsquo;s a handy way for people to look a little more closely at the number of factors to extract (although, I would argue not enough).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking Both Ways - Infix Functions</title>
      <link>/2017/02/05/looking-both-ways---infix-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/05/looking-both-ways---infix-functions/</guid>
      <description>In your R journeys you may have come across some interesting functions like apply statements or even lm. One function that is particularly helpful (and interesting) is the piping operator (%&amp;gt;%) from the magrittr pacakge. You may have noticed that the piping operator is similar to the matrix multiplcation operator %*%, in that they are both sandwitch functions (may or may not be trying to coin this term right now), as the function call is/are a symbol(s) enclosed by a % on both times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem With Backward Selection</title>
      <link>/2017/01/22/the-problem-with-backward-selection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/22/the-problem-with-backward-selection/</guid>
      <description>Q: What does modeling the number of people buying gelato in Venice using cultural data and environmental attributes have in common with assessing which measures of reading speed are most related to glaucoma propensity?
A: A strong need for variable selection.
Whenever we consider estimating the relationship between two variables, say \(x\) and \(y\), we need to contemplate what other factors may be associated with those of interest and whether or not to include them in our model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post!</title>
      <link>/2017/01/21/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/21/first-post/</guid>
      <description>After a few Wordpress blogs, a Django experiment and a test of Flask, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to get my feet wet with Jekyll. Thanks to Dean for the beautiful Jekyll template, beautiful-jekyll, the site is already looking nice. Hope you come along for the ride!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Hacking together my first web app - Rental Tensor       code{white-space: pre;} pre:not([class]) { background-color: white; }  if (window.hljs) { hljs.configure({languages: []}); hljs.initHighlightingOnLoad(); if (document.readyState &amp;&amp; document.readyState === &#34;complete&#34;) { window.setTimeout(function() { hljs.initHighlighting(); }, 0); } }  h1 { font-size: 34px; } h1.title { font-size: 38px; } h2 { font-size: 30px; } h3 { font-size: 24px; } h4 { font-size: 18px; } h5 { font-size: 16px; } h6 { font-size: 12px; } .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>